Finding Aid for Raymond Cazallis Davis papers, 1850-1917
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Raymond Cazallis Davis papers 1850-1917
Davis, R. C. (Raymond Cazallis), b. 1836.
851255 Aa 2; UAm; UAx
Librarian of University of Michigan. Correspondence, including material on library administration, collection development, opening a new library in 1883, and the exhibition of University of Michigan professor's books at the 1893 World's Fair; also family correspondence, including letters discussing travels and Civil War service of family members; and photographs.
6 linear feet
2 folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. John T. Norton (donor no. 2284 ) and came to the library in multiple accessions, 1955-1957.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Raymond Cazallis Davis was born at Cushing, Maine, June 23, 1836, son of George and Catherine (Young) Davis. After his mother's death in 1849, his father, who was a sea captain, took young Davis on a cruise around the world which lasted two years. Later, in 1869 he published a volume of his experiences entitled "Reminiscences of a Voyage around the World." In 1855 Davis entered the University of Michigan. Unfortunately, towards the end of the second year his studies were interrupted by a severe illness which incapacitated him for serious work for some years. In 1868 he returned to the University as assistant librarian. At the end of four years the Regents offered him the position of chief librarian. As acceptance would have involved the displacement of the incumbent, he declined the office, instead leaving Ann Arbor for Maine.
In 1877 the office of librarian at the University having fallen vacant, Davis was again offered the position. He now felt free to accept it. During his long term of service extending over twenty-eight years the Library grew steadily in size and professionalism. Early in his career, a new library building was built and occupied. In addition, Davis developed the card catalog and was aggressive in expanding the holdings of the library. In 1905, at his own request, he retired and was made librarian emeritus and lecturer on bibliography, a course he had instituted in 1882. In 1881 the Regents of the University conferred upon him the honorary degree of Master of Arts. Davis died June 10, 1919.
The collection includes correspondence; files relating to his career as chief librarian of the University of Michigan; personal and biographical materials; and speeches, essays, and writings.
Subjects:
California--Description and travel.; Delta Kappa Epsilon. Omicron Chapter (University of Michigan); Libraries--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Literary Adelphi (University of Michigan).; Voyages and travels.; Travelers.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan. Library.; University of Michigan--Students--Correspondence.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1851-1860.; World's Columbian Exposition (1893: Chicago, Ill.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Davis, Ellen Regal.; Davis, R. C. (Raymond Cazallis), b. 1836.; Living rooms--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Contributors:
Alger, R. A. (Russell Alexander), 1836-1907.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Boise, James Robinson, 1815-1895.; Davis, Ferdinand, b. 1840.; Davis, Frederick.; Davis, George.; Demmon, Isaac Newton, 1842-1920.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Dewey, Melvil, 1851-1931.; Finney, Byron Alfred, 1849-1938.; Flanders, George A.; Frieze, Henry S. (Henry Simmons), 1817-1889.; Hay, John, 1838-1905.; McMillan, James, 1838-1902.; Rogers, Henry Wade, 1853-1926.; Ten Brook, Andrew, 1814-1899.; Williams, George Palmer, 1802-1881.
Genre Terms:
Ambrotypes.; Daguerreotypes.; Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Correspondence
  - 1850-1859 (Box 1)
    (include family letter, April 18, 1850, describing travels and visit to San Francisco; letter from George Davis, November 29, 1857, regarding Delta Kappa Epsilon, Literary Adelphi, professors George P. Williams and James R. Boise, and a prank involving animals in College Hall; letter from James R. Boise, 1859, and letter from Henry S. Frieze, February 3, 1859)
  - 1860-1864 (Box 1)
    (include letter November 1860 describing election day in Boston)
  - 1865-1869 (Box 1)
    (include letter, June 15, 1862, of George Flanders telling of his Civil War experiences with Co. F, 8th New Hampshire Infantry; letters, 1861-1862, of Ferdinand Davis while with the 7th New Hampshire Infantry; letter from A. Calloway Nesbitt to Mrs. Davis, October 18, 1865, containing an account of the death of R.C. Davis' brother, Byron Davis)
  - 1872-1877 (Box 1)
    (include letter, April 20, 1874, regarding removal of Andrew Ten Brook as librarian; letters, June 28 and October 12, 1877, from James B. Angell regarding Davis' appointment)
  - January-June 1878 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1878 (Box 1)
  - January-February 1879 (Box 1)
  - April-July 1879 (Box 1)
  - August-December 1879 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1880 (Box 1)
  - April-August 1880 (Box 1)
  - September-December 1880 (Box 1)
  - January-April 1881 (Box 1)
  - May-September 1881 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1881 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1882 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1882 (Box 1)
  - July-September 1882 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1882 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1883 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1883 (Box 1)
  - July-September 1883 (Box 1)
  - October 1883 (Box 1)
  - January-February 1884 (Box 1)
  - March-May 1884 (Box 1)
  - June-September 1884 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1884 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1885 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1885 (Box 1)
  - July-September 1885 (Box 1)
  - October-December 1885 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1886 (Box 2)
  - April-June 1886 (Box 2)
  - July-September 1886 (Box 2)
  - October-December 1886 (Box 2)
  - January-April 1887 (Box 2)
    (include letter from Melvil Dewey, February 7)
  - May-October 1887 (Box 2)
    (include letter from Melvil Dewey, May 5, May 30)
  - November-December 1887 (Box 2)
    (include letter from Melvil Dewey, November 17, November 28)
  - January-March 1888 (Box 2)
  - April-June 1888 (Box 2)
    (include letter from Melvil Dewey, April 23, April 24)
  - July-October 1888 (Box 2)
  - November-December 1888 (Box 2)
    (include letter from Melvil Dewey, December 15, and from John Dewey, November 2)
  - January-February 1889 (Box 2)
  - March-April 1889 (Box 2)
  - May-June 1889 (Box 2)
  - July-October 1889 (Box 2)
  - November-December 1889 (Box 2)
  - January-March 1890 (Box 2)
  - April-June 1890 (Box 2)
  - July-October 1890 (Box 2)
  - November-December 1890 (Box 2)
  - January-March 1891 (Box 2)
  - April-June 1891 (Box 2)
  - July-September 1891 (Box 2)
  - October-December 1891 (Box 2)
  - January-February 1892 (Box 2)
  - March-May 1892 (Box 2)
  - June-September 1892 (Box 3)
  - October-December 1892 (Box 3)
    (include letter from Senator James McMillan, December 13)
  - January-March 1893 (Box 3)
  - April-June 1893 (Box 3)
    (include letter from Henry Wade Rogers, June 9)
  - July-September 1893 (Box 3)
  - October-December 1893 (Box 3)
  - January-February 1894 (Box 3)
  - March-April 1894 (Box 3)
  - May-June 1894 (Box 3)
  - July-August 1894 (Box 3)
  - September-October 1894 (Box 3)
  - November-December 1894 (Box 3)
  - January-February 1895 (Box 3)
  - March-April 1895 (Box 3)
  - May-June 1895 (Box 3)
  - July-September 1895 (Box 3)
  - October-December 1895 (Box 3)
  - January-February 1896 (Box 3)
  - March-April 1896 (Box 3)
  - May-June 1896 (Box 3)
  - July-September 1896 (Box 3)
    (include letter from Isaac Demmon, August 20)
  - October-December 1896 (Box 3)
  - January-March 1897 (Box 4)
  - April-June 1897 (Box 4)
  - July-September 1897 (Box 4)
  - October-December 1897 (Box 4)
  - January-February 1898 (Box 4)
  - March-April 1898 (Box 4)
  - May-June 1898 (Box 4)
  - July-September 1898 (Box 4)
  - October-December 1898 (Box 4)
  - January-March 1899 (Box 4)
  - April-June 1899 (Box 4)
  - July-September 1899 (Box 4)
  - October-December 1899 (Box 4)
  - January-February 1900 (Box 4)
  - March-April 1900 (Box 4)
  - May-June 1900 (Box 4)
  - July-October 1900 (Box 4)
  - November-December 1900 (Box 4)
  - January-March 1901 (Box 4)
  - April-May 1901 (Box 4)
  - July-December 1901 (Box 4)
  - January-March 1902 (Box 4)
  - April-August 1902 (Box 4)
  - September-December 1902 (Box 4)
  - January-February 1903 (Box 4)
  - March-April 1903 (Box 4)
  - May-July 1903 (Box 4)
  - August-October 1903 (Box 4)
  - November-December 1903 (Box 4)
    (include letter from Russell Alger, November 14, with enclosure of letter from John Hay)
  - January-March 1904 (Box 5)
  - April-May 1904 (Box 5)
  - June-August 1904 (Box 5)
    (include letter, July 3, by Mrs. R.C. Davis to Mrs. Edwin Goodrich re: health and summer resort in Maine; also letter June 16 from Isaac Demmon)
  - September-December 1904 (Box 5)
  - January-February 1905 (Box 5)
  - March-April 1905 (Box 5)
  - May-June 1905 (Box 5)
  - July-December 1905 (Box 5)
  - 1906 (Box 5)
  - 1910-1922 (scattered) (Box 5)
  - Undated and various (Box 5)
- University of Michigan Library
  - Manuscript, report, other items relating to opening of the new library 1883, as well as miscellanea concerning the operation of the library, duties of the librarian and the assistant (Box 5)
  - Annual report of the librarian to the Board of Regents 1885 (Box 5)
  - Annual report of the librarian to the Board of Regents 1892 (Box 5)
  - Annual report of the librarian to the Board of Regents 1893 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence with various book companies about an exhibit of University of Michigan professors' books at the Chicago World's Fair 1893 (Box 5)
  - B.A. Finney's report to Davis on annual circulation 1895 (Box 5)
  - B.A. Finney's annual report to Davis on circulation 1903 (Box 5)
  - Building of Carnegie Libraries, correspondence regarding 1902-1904 (Box 5)
  - Annual reports of B.A. Finney and H.O. Severance 1905 (Box 5)
  - Bills and receipts 1870-1906, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - War Department forms acknowledging return of books loaned to University of Michigan Library (Box 5)
  - Library miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Biographical / Personal
  - Autobiography and related, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Commonplace book with notes on sermons, etc. (Box 5)
  - Miscellanea-will, cemetery deed, land grants (Box 5)
  - Senate memorial for R.C. Davis (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts-poem, bibliography, bibliographical data (Box 5)
  - Photographs, mainly portraits of Davis and his wife and at his residence (Box 5)
    (see also oversize folder UAm and special care folder UAx)
- Speeches, essays, writings
  - On Thompson's Rocks-The Idemic Sin (Box 6)
  - The Librarian's Relation to Material Things (read before the Columbia Library School) (Box 6)
  - The Books of 1886 (Box 6)
  - Address read before the Student Christian Association undated (Box 6)
  - Maine Artillery on a Lark-a story (Box 6)
  - Interview with the Animals (Box 6)
  - The Diamond and the Pearl (Box 6)
  - The History of Philosophy (Box 6)
  - Pink and Pedro-(story) (Box 6)
  - Tales of a Wayside (Box 6)
  - The Twin Voyages of Captains Teel and Rawley (Box 6)
  - Cornelius-A Tale of Ancient Rome.
    - Book I Lucullus (outline) (Box 6)
    - Book II Demetrius (Box 6)
    - Book IV The Fortunate Isles (Box 6)
    - Book V The Battle of Actium (Box 6)
  - Maine Yarns (Box 6)
  - References and notes for Practical and Intellectual Bibliography and other subjects (Box 6)
  - Capture and Recapture (story) (Box 6)
  - Richard Hooker-an analysis of Hooker as writer (Box 6)
  - Unselfish nature of bibliographical labor in the last century (2 copies) (Box 6)
  - The Williams Emeritus Professorship Fund (Box 6)
  - Prefatory matter of books (Box 6)
  - An Irish Idyll (story) (Box 6)
  - Introductory to Nature and the Supernatural (Box 6)
  - Sea Serpent (2 copies) (Box 6)
  - Novel reading (essay) (Box 6)
  - Original manuscript of the History of Books, including omitted material (Box 6)
  - Notebooks on the history of books and printing, 9 tablets (Box 6)